# Michael B. James, Ph.D. ■ hello@michaelbjames.com | ↑ michaelbjames.com | □ michaelbjames | □ michael-b-james

## **Research Mission**

Building the next generation of Human-AI programming environments requires a deep understanding both of how Al-assistants operate and of how programmers use them. My work spans both, through my experience with Al-agents, Programming Languages techniques, and Human-Computer Interactions methodologies. I identify developer-centric challenges and overcome them with a novel combination of stochastic and formal techniques.

## Education -

## University of California, San Diego

- · Ph.D., Computer Science 2018-2024
- · M.S. Computer Science 2021

Advisor: Nadia Polikarpova

#### **Tufts University**

· B.S. Computer Science 2015

## **Publications**

- **Exploratory Phenomena in Program Synthesis.** Michael B. James. 2024. [THESIS]:
- Validating AI-Generated Code with Live Programming. Kasra Ferdowsi\*, Ruangiangian (Lisa) Huang\*, [LEAP]: Michael B. James, Nadia Polikarpova, Sorin Lerner. CHI. May 2024.
- Grounded Copilot: How Programmers Interact with Code-Generating Models. Shraddha Barke\*, [GCP]: Michael B. James\*, Nadia Polikarpova. OOPSLA. October 2023. Distinguished Paper Award
- Program Recognition in Synthesis. Michael B. James, Nadia Polikarpova. PLATEAU. November 2021. [PRS]:
- Digging for Fold: Synthesis-aided API Discovery for Haskell. Michael B. James, Zheng Guo, Ziteng Wang, Shivani Dosh, Hila Peleg, Ranjit Jhala, Nadia Polikarpova. OOPSLA. November 2020.
- Program Synthesis by Type-Guided Abstraction Refinement. Zheng Guo, Michael B. James, David Justo, [TYGAR]: Jiaxiao Zhou, Ziteng Wang, Ranjit Jhala, Nadia Polikarpova 47th ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages (POPL 2020). January 2020.

## **Work Experience**

Senior AI Research Scientist. Sailplane PBC. New York City. Jul 2024 - current

- · Designed and implemented new highly-parallel AI agent for programming
- · Built and managed large VSCode extension empowering AI engineers
- · Compared agent against SOTA with new dataset and novel evaluation using LLM judges
- · Conducted contextual inquiry studies for UX development of tools.

Research Intern. Microsoft. Remote. Summer 2022

Mentors: Ariun Radhakrishna, Gustavo Soares

- · Worked with the PROSE team on novel interactive program synthesis tool for API migrations.
- · Gathered changing product goals from several internal customers in concrete action plan

Software Engineer II. Jana Mobile. Boston, Massachusetts. Feb 2017 - Jun 2018

- · Redesigned revenue reporting pipeline for live business metrics
- · Designed & implemented user profile data collection, from Cassandra DB to Android+Chromium frontend
- · Productionized data scientist analyses for metrics and alert generation on business status
- · Managed data scientists' APIs for product metrics, including Kafka pipelines

Software Engineer I. Uber Technologies. San Francisco. Jul 2015 - Dec 2016

- · Owned business.uber.com. Led service migration to React.
- · Lead team migration to golang, with a new anti-fraud microservice.
- · Managed and contributed to 12 microservices.
- · Gathered requirements from designers and backend for feature implementation
- · Conducted technical interviews to hire for team

## **Research Projects**

**Human-AI Collaborative Programming** 2021-2024

Our groundbreaking study identified how programmers use Copilot: they either *accelerate* through a task, or use the tool to *explore* their problem space<sup>[GCP]</sup>. Our findings identified difficulty in validating Al-generated code, but our technique with live programming eases this difficulty<sup>[LEAP]</sup>. Current work-inprogress highlights the "wisdom of the crowds" of an LLM to assist in design space exploration.

Type Directed Synthesis in Haskell 2018-2021

Our novel synthesis technique generates Haskell programs that are guaranteed to satisfy the user's intent quickly by using abstract refinements<sup>[TYGAR]</sup>. A user-study proves that our multi-modal search with examples and tests aids program comprehension, allowing a user to complete more tasks<sup>[H+]</sup>. A followup study reinforces the need for tool-assisted code validation<sup>[PRS]</sup>.

## **Talks**

**Grounded Copilot: How Programmers Interact with Code-Generating Models**. 2023 - OOPSLA (Cascais, Portugal)

Program Recognition in Synthesis. 2021 - PLATEAU (Carnegie Mellon University)

Digging for Fold: Synthesis-aided API Discovery for Haskell. 2021 - OOPSLA (Chicago), 2020 - OOPSLA 2020 (virtual)

Component-based Type Driven Synthesis. 2019 - University of California, San Diego

## Teaching -

**Graduate Teaching Assistant** (UC San Diego)

Courses: undergraduate and graduate programming

languages.

Fall 2023, Spring 2022, Spring 2021, Fall 2019.

Supervisor: Nadia Polikarpova

**Undergraduate Teaching Assistant** (Tufts University)

Course: undergraduate programming languages

Fall 2014.

Supervisor: Kathleen Fisher

### Service

Reviewer: CHI 2024, PLATEAU 2024

Student Volunteer Co-Chair: PLDI 2023, 2024 Artifact Evaluation: ICFP 2020, ICFP 2021

### Skills-

Python, Typescript, Haskell, Elixir, Program Synthesis, Artificial Intelligence, AI Agents, Distributed Systems, User Research, Quantitative Research, Qualitative Research, Evaluation, Data Science, Compilers, Type Systems, Web development, git, jira, react